A Guide to the Wallace Buttrick Papers FA026
Rockefeller Archive Center
Wallace Buttrick papers
1888-1926
Rockefeller Archive Center
Buttrick, Wallace
FA026
0.35 Cubic Feet
Arrangement note
The material in this collection is arranged chronologically, with the clippings and the scrapbooks at the end.
Biographical/Historical note
Wallace Buttrick was born on October 3, 1853, on a farm in Potsdam, New York. In 1857, his family moved to Madrid, New York, and later to Ogdensburg where he spent most of his youth.
Mr. Buttrick attended the Ogdensburg Academy and later the Potsdam Normal School. His education was interrupted when his father became ill, and he then secured a job as a messenger in the State Capitol at Albany. This proved unsuitable, and in 1875 he took a position as railroad mail agent between Rome, New York, and Ogdensburg.
In 1880, Mr. Buttrick moved to Rochester where he entered the Divinity School. His first pastorate was the First Baptist Church of New Haven. He was always interested in the West, and he moved to the First Church of St. Paul, Minnesota in 1890. While in Minnesota, Mr. Buttrick engaged in lively controversies with the city administration. In 1892, he moved east to the Emmanuel Church of Albany where he stayed for nearly 10 years.
In 1902, Mr. Buttrick joined the General Education Board as Secretary.
Wallace Buttrick died on May 27, 1926.
Scope and Contents note
The Wallace Buttrick collection covers the period from 1888 to 1926.
This collection contains material on the Buttrick family history, Wallace Buttrick's several pastorates, his early work with the China Medical Board, and a trip to England in 1917.
Materials included are two unidentified manuscripts, resolutions, clippings, and a pamphlet.
Important subjects include family history; organization of the China Medical Board; trip to England in 1917; church interests; St. Paul, Minnesota, controversies; education; and Henry Lyman Morehouse.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Wallace Buttrick were deposited with the Rockefeller Foundation Archives in July 1967 by Mrs. Charles Merrill.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 2A 01
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for scholarly research without restriction.
Saint Paul (Minn.); Religion; England; Education; China Medical Board (U.S); Buttrick, Wallace; Morehouse, Henry Lyman
- Genealogy, 1616-1895 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  5 x 8 index card with handwritten genealogy of the Buttrick family.
- Family History, 1616-1836 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Five page typescript family history of the Buttrick family.
- Wallace Buttrick, 1853-1902 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Thirty-nine page typescript history of Wallace Buttrick and immediate family.
- Emmanuel Church Resolution, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Resolution adopted by the Church Board on the occasion of Mr. Buttrick's departure from the Albany church.
- China Medical Board, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Wallace Buttrick's recollections on his service with the China Medical Board.
- England, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Recollection of Wallace Buttrick's trip to England at the request of the American ambassador to England.
- "What is Education" by Wallace Buttrick, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Reprint from "The Peabody Journal of Education," vol. 3, no. 3, November 1925. States what education is "in the form of five propositions" I. All Education is Self-Education II. Capacity for Intelligent Self-Direction III. Trained Capacity for Sustained Attention IV. Education is Never Finished; It Is As Long As Life V. The Object of Education is Character, Not Efficiency
- "The Tribute Beautiful" by Wallace Buttrick, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Excerpt from a biography of Henry Lyman Morehouse, in which Buttrick recalls Morehouse.
- Miscellaneous Clippings, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Clippings primarily dealing with Buttrick's tenure in St. Paul, Minnesota.
- Miscellaneous Clippings, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Clippings consist primarily of obituaries and testimonials of Buttrick, who died May 27, 1926.
- Scrapbook, 1888-1902 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Articles/contributions by Buttrick to various newspapers.
- Scrapbook, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Articles concerning St. Paul, Minnesota controversy.
- Scrapbook, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Articles and publications on the General Education Board.